[hi] Hello, in this short video, I will tell you about the course coverage or outline of the
[hi] course on electrical machines 1. In this course, primarily two topics will be covered.
[hi] is on transformers and the other one is on DC machines. Transformers when I say we will
[hi] be mainly discussing about the power transformers, the transformers that operate at 50 hertz
[hi] and transformer being a static device its efficiency can be very large may be 99 percent
[hi] for large transformers is this value of efficiency is not uncommon.
[hi] And transformer as you know, it transforms one level of voltage to another level voltage
[hi] keeping the frequency same and power in both the primary and secondary windings in a
[hi] to winding transformers that also remain same. And transformer is an integral part of the
[hi] modern day power transmission and distribution systems and it is widely used. Whenever
[hi] you need a change of level of voltage a transformer is to be used.
[hi] Now, therefore, it is worthwhile to study transformer slightly in detail.
[hi] So, we will begin with the operating principle of a transformer and then we will discuss about
[hi] the concept of ideal transformer.
[hi] And before we really start transformer, another small topics we will just review that is called
[hi] the magnetic circuit analysis, a magnetic structure there will be coil soon, if it carries current
[hi] how to calculate the flux that will be established in the core or conversely if flux in the core
[hi] for a desired flux in the core, how much current is needed in the coil, these are the topics
[hi] of what is called magnetic circuit analysis. So, we will briefly discuss about that.
[hi] Then transformer, a two winding transformer basically is a two coupled coils with self
[hi] inductances, L 1, L 2 mutual inductance M. Therefore, a discussion on coupled coils and inductance
[hi] values out there related will be discussed. After that we will start with an ideal transformer
[hi] and ideal transformer is a transformer which has no losses, no winding resistance, no
[hi] leakage flux and then we shall try to find out the equivalent circuit of an ideal transformer
[hi] And ideal transformer is really ideal that does not exist in practice.
[hi] Then based on the knowledge gained from the analysis of ideal transformer, we shall take
[hi] up a practical transformer which is non-ideal and then we shall bring all the realities present
[hi] in a practical transformer and add that thing to an ideal transformer to get the equivalent
[hi] circuit of a say two winding transformer. So, equivalent circuit development is an important
[hi] part of the course. So, EMF equations, then feather diagram of course, we will naturally
[hi] follow, then you develop the equivalent circuit of a transformer starting from the ideal
[hi] transformer that we will do. Once you get the equivalent circuit of a transformer, then
[hi] you can predict the performance of the transformer under various conditions, no load, full load
[hi] conditions that is for a given input voltage, what will be the output terminal voltage if
[hi] a particular load is connected across the secondary of a transformer. Those analysis can
[hi] easily be done and also we can predict the efficiency of the transformer when it is
[hi] operating at a particular load. Then there is another important topic which is called
[hi] the regulation of a transformer that also can be estimated from the equivalent circuit
[hi] of a transformer. Now, the moment we say that a transformer has got an equivalent circuit
[hi] means that there will be several resistances primary winding resistance primary leakage
[hi] reactance secondary resistance secondary leakage reactance and magnetizing branch of impedance
[hi] etcetera. Therefore, for a practical transformer how to determine or estimate rather the equivalent
[hi] circuit parameters of a transformer that we will discuss. In fact, by doing some simple
[hi] test called open circuit and short circuit test on a transformer, the equivalent circuit
[hi] parameters can easily be estimated. Therefore, a transformer, if I know the equivalent
[hi] circuit, I can predict the performance of the transformer at a given loading condition
[hi] of the transformer and also I can estimate what will be the voltages available. So, this
[hi] will be the topics of the transformer. Now, transformers may be of various types. For
[hi] example, we will start our discussion with a single phase transformer. Then as you know
[hi] our power system is after all a three phase system. Therefore, three phase transformers
[hi] are also widely used. So, we will then talk about the three phase transformers its constructional
[hi] features and the connections the transformer primary winding may be connected in star,
[hi] engineering delta or vice versa or start start delta delta, what are the implications
[hi] of those connections and a three phase transformer connections are specified what is called
[hi] by a vector group. So, we will also learn about the vector group of a transformer and
[hi] give in a three phase transformers, how to correctly connect them in a particular fashion
[hi] for example, Y D 1, D Y 11 these are called vector groups, this also we will discuss in
[hi] great length. Then equivalent circuit of a three phase transformers will be similar to
[hi] that of a single phase transformer, only thing per phase based analysis is carried out.
[hi] So, all the things like regulation, efficiency calculations, they are similar to that one.
[hi] So, two winding transformers, single phase, then three phase transformers, we will switch
[hi] over and there is another class of power transformers, that is called auto transformer.
[hi] That is also very interesting.
[hi] So, auto transformer essentially has a single coil where supply is given across the whole
[hi] of the coil and through some tapings the output are taken.
[hi] Therefore, a portion of the coil or winding is common to both primary and secondary.
[hi] So, how to analyze the performance of an auto transformer, its equivalent circuit.
[hi] these are the things we will discuss and if you can change the level of the voltage from
[hi] one value to another, which keeps of course frequency same, you then learn that it can
[hi] be done in two ways. You can use a winding transformers or you can use an auto transformer.
[hi] The moment you have got two options, the question is which one to choose, should we choose
[hi] winding transformer to change a voltage of 200 volt to 100 volt or should we use an
[hi] auto transformer which can also change the level of voltage from 200 to 100 volt.
[hi] Therefore, there will be some issues or we must understand under what condition to use
[hi] an auto transformer or under what condition we use a winding transformer.
[hi] three phase auto transformers are also used. Therefore, these are the main topics. Apart
[hi] from that, we will discuss about the parallel operation of transformers both single phase
[hi] and three phase. What are the conditions under which two transformers can be connected
[hi] in parallel and why the transformers are connected in parallel at all? These are the things
[hi] we will also discuss. After we have discussed if we get some time, then we will also discuss
[hi] about some special phenomena which occurs in a transformer. For example, switching transients
[hi] in a transformer, magnetic in rush current. These are some topics which if time permits
[hi] I will definitely discuss. So, this is in nutshell about the transformers and also at the
[hi] end I will sketch a transformer where what are the fittings they are connected, how to
[hi] cool a transformer, this I will just touch upon.
[hi] That main point is the how to analyze a circuit, power circuit which involves a transformer
[hi] inside that is the whole idea anyway. So, this will be the about 30 units or 13 to half
[hi] an hour will be consumed by transformer. Next 30 units we will discuss about DC machines.
[hi] Remember, transformer is also a machine, but it is called a static machine.
[hi] As I told you, efficiency of transformer could be very high, because it is static, there
[hi] is no rotating part in it, therefore, its efficiency can be very high.
[hi] On the other hand, rotating machines, which takes electrical input power, for example,
[hi] motor operation and then it will convert that input electrical energy into mechanical
[hi] energy in case of motors or in any rotating generator the input power will be mechanical
[hi] power input and output power will be electrical. So, rotating machines are of various kinds
[hi] of various kinds, for example, DC machines, AC machines, primary divisions are like that.
[hi] Now, DC machine will be the topic that we will be discussing here. So, the constructional
[hi] features of a DC machine, any rotating machine we will have two structures. So, one is the
[hi] stator and another is the rotor part which rotates. On the stator there will be windings, on
[hi] the rotors there will be also windings and when the machine will be operating both this
[hi] stator and rotor coils will be carrying current and they will produce fields magnetic fields
[hi] magnetic poles and they will interact with each other giving you torque that is the in
[hi] short the story about all the rotating machines.
[hi] Now in case of DC machines the stator windings will be wound on projected poles and it is
[hi] very simple, simple windings and that winding will be excited by as the name suggest with
[hi] DC or batteries constant current will be flowing.
[hi] The armature winding is somewhat complicated.
[hi] In the sense unlike AC machine winding armature windings will have coils no doubt housed
[hi] on the slots in the rotor, but these windings will be terminated on commutator segments and
[hi] output of the armature terminals are taken from glasses ok. Therefore, the constructional
[hi] features of decimation is very important. After we have discussed the constructional features,
[hi] we will develop the EMF and torque equations of decimations which may operate both as
[hi] motor or as generator and these things I will take simultaneously these two options.
[hi] Then the characteristics of DC generators and characteristics of DC machines will take
[hi] up. Then, we will talk about the equivalent circuit of the DC machine and how to calculate
[hi] the efficiency of a DC machine, what kind of test we have to perform. Now, DC machines
[hi] can be classified as a shunt machine, series machine or a compound machines. So, the characteristics
[hi] of all these types of machines and their relative advantage and disadvantages we will discuss.
[hi] So, armature reaction for example, an important topic in this machine. When armature carries
[hi] current, it will also create flux and as I told you any flux component along the brass
[hi] axis creates problem. So, that is called commutation problem. The
[hi] effects of armature reaction, how to nullify them in a DC machine, I will also discuss
[hi] you can use the compensating widening or inter poles. So, the characteristics of separately
[hi] excited DC machine shunt, excited DC machines and other series generators are also there,
[hi] limited use. So, those characteristics will discuss. Similarly, shunt motor, series motor
[hi] and compound motors, the characteristics of them will briefly discuss. And if time permits,
[hi] we will discuss about several kind of testing on decimations including Hopkinson test.
[hi] So, I hope you will like this course and this course will be supported by some lecture
[hi] notes that I will write and provide you as lecture proceeds and we will have interaction
[hi] among ourselves so that any queries on your part will be discussed specially and also
[hi] So there will be tutorial session, extensive tutorial session on this course.
[hi] Last word, in case of AC machines, equivalent circuit is somewhat difficult, involved.
[hi] Analysis calculations are also difficult.
[hi] In case of DC machines, it is the other way round.
[hi] Construction is difficult, but computation is very simple and this is how the lectures
[hi] will go on. Thank you so much for your patient hearing.